Finding Aid for Walter Pinkus papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Walter Pinkus Papers 1960-2011
Pinkus, Walter
1 oversize boxes
7 linear feet
2014146 Aa 2
Walter Pinkus was an Engineer in Research for the University of Michigan's Atmospheric, Oceanic, and Space Sciences Department's Space Physics Research Laboratory from 1966 to 1996. At the lab he conducted design work on instruments built for various National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) missions. The collection contains correspondence, schematics, project books, and research reports relating to the projects Pinkus worked on. Included in the collection are papers related to the San Marco program, Galileo spacecraft, and the High Resolution Doppler Imager (HRDI).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection was donated by Walter Pinkus (donor no. 10625 ) in September 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Walter Pinkus was an Engineer in Research for the University of Michigan's Atmospheric, Oceanic, and Space Sciences Department's Space Physics Research Laboratory from 1966 to 1996. He received a Bachelor's of Science in Electrical Engineering from Swarthmore College in 1965. The following year Pinkus attended the University of Michigan where he worked in the Brain Research Laboratory and the Space Physics Research Laboratory. In 1974 he received a Master of Science in Engineering with a specialization in analog and digital circuits and system design. Pinkus continued working for the Space Physics Research Laboratory after completing his master's degree. He served as a design engineer on portions of the conceptual, system, and detail design of analog, digital, and analog to digital/digital to analog (A/D/A) interfaces of many laboratory programs. Pinkus worked on designs, builds, and analyses data on aerospace scientific instrumentation primarily under contract to NASA. He served as a project engineer for, Venus Orbiter Imaging Radar, and Dynamics Explorer for the Langmuir Probe Instrument. He also served as the co-project engineer for the Pioneer Venus Orbiter and the Atmosphere Explorer Thermosphere Probe. Pinkus's projects were used to study the Earth's upper atmosphere, and the surfaces of Venus, Mars, and Jupiter. Pinkus retired from the University of Michigan in 1999.
The collection is arranged into two series: Correspondence and Related Materials, and Research Materials. The Research Materials series is further divided into four subseries.
The Walter Pinkus papers encompasses Pinkus's time at the University of Michigan's Space Physics Research Laboratory. The papers date from 1965 to 1996and include correspondence, schematics, project books, and research reports on instruments built for various National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) missions. Included in the collection are notes from the Galileo space probe project, the San Marco program, Mars Upper Atmosphere Dynamics, Energetics, and Evaluation (MUADEE) project. The arrangement of the collection follows Pinkus's arrangement of the materials.
Subjects:
Engineering--Research.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Space sciences.; University of Michigan. Space Physics Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan--Staff.; University of Michigan--Research.
Genre Terms:
Diagrams.; Photographs.
- Correspondence and Related Materials
  The Correspondence and Related Materials series (1960-2011, 0.5 linear feet), contains materials relating to his personal correspondences and various project designs. Included are a number of responses from United States Congressmen regarding funding for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, Pinkus's resume from 1996. The series also contains digital content that includes performance reviews, reports relating to his research projects, and email correspondence.
  - 1960-1992, 17 folders (Box 1)
  - 1986-2011, .ZIP file
- Research Materials 1969-2011
  The Research Materials series (1969-2011, 6.5 linear feet), contains materials related to the projects Pinkus worked on at the University of Michigan. The series is divided into four subseries that reflect upon Pinkus's personal organization of his records: Atmosphere Explorer, Dynamics Explorer, and San Marco; Galileo Probe and MUADEE; HRDI Balloon Flight Instrument;, and TIDI, TOMS, Balloon Rotator, Antarctic Magnetometer, and MFPI.
  - Atmosphere Explorer; Dynamics Explorer; and San Marco 1969-1986
    The Atmosphere Explorer, Dynamics Explorer, and San Marco (1969-1986, 2.7 linear feet), subseries contains materials related to the Atmosphere Explorer (AE), Dynamics Explorer (DE), and San Marco projects. The Atmosphere Explorer and Dynamics Explorer programs studied the photochemistry and dynamics of the Earth's upper atmosphere, including the ionosphere. The series contains schematics, drawings, test reports, and research notes on various instruments and instrument components that went into the explorer programs. There is also similar material relating to the San Marco Programme. San Marco was an Italian satellite launch program conducted from the early 1960s into the late 1980s.
    - 1969-1986, 12 folders (Box 1)
    - 1966-1979, 14 folders (Box 2)
    - San Marco WATE Booklet 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - OGO-F Thorad/Acena 11 Operations Summary Booklet 1969 (Box 7)
    - OGO F-04 Prototype Units Master Print Booklet 1969 (Box 1)
    - OGO F-04 Neutral Mass Spectrometer Booklet 1978 (Box 1)
    - Design Verification Unit Signal Processor Pioneer Venus GSFC/OETP "5963-01" As Modified for Dynamics Explorer-B "LANG" Booklet 1981 (Box 1)
    - Design Verification Unit Signal Processor Pioneer Venus GSFC/OETP "5963-01" Reference Only Copy Booklet 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1980, 18 folders (Box 3)
    - 1976-1977, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Galileo Probe and MUADEE 1974-1995
    The Galileo Probe and MUADEE (1974-1995,1 linear foot), subseries contains information regarding the Galileo Mission and the Mars Upper Atmosphere Dynamics, Energetics, and Evaluation (MUADEE) discovery mission. The Galileo mission, alternately called the Jupiter Probe and the Galileo Probe in Pinkus's notes, was the first mission to measure Jupiter's atmosphere and conduct long-term observations of the Jovian system from orbit. Included are correspondence, meeting notes, schematics, and research notes regarding the building of instruments for the probe. The Mars Upper Atmosphere Dynamics Energetics, and Evaluation discovery mission, abbreviated MUADEE in Pinkus's notes, was a low cost mission to investigate the upper atmosphere of Mars in order to better understand how Mars has evolved over geological time. The series contains notes, cost proposals, and schematics relating to the development of MUADEE.
    - 1978-1995, 14 folders (Box 4)
    - 1979-1982, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - MARS Data System Booklet 1969-1971 (Box 7)
    - Galileo Schematics Booklet 1979 (Box 1)
  - HRDI Balloon Flight Instrument (Box 5)
    The HRDI Balloon Flight Instrument (1972-1993 1 linear foot), subseries contains information regarding the High Resolution Doppler Imager (HRDI). The HRDI was one of the instruments aboard the Upper Atmospheric Research Satellite, which was launched by NASA to study the Earth's stratosphere and mesosphere. The HRDI observed the emission and absorption lines of molecular oxygen. The UARS was launched in September 1991 and deactivated December 2005. Included are correspondence, meeting notes, schematics, and research notes regarding the building of the HRDI Balloon.
    - 1972-1993, 21 folders (Box 5)
    - 1978-1985, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - GAS Surface EXPT Control Logic Design Booklet 1968-1969 (Box 7)
    - UARS Project Data Book Booklet 1987 (Box 7)
    - Critical Design Review HRDI and UARS Booklet 1986 (Box 7)
    - Preliminary Design Review HRDI and UARS Booklet 1985 (Box 7)
    - HRDI FLT DWG Book 1986-1990 (Box 7)
  - TIDI, TOMS, Balloon Rotator, Antarctic Magnetometer, and MFPI
    The TIDI, TOMS, Balloon Rotator, Antarctic Magnetometer, and MFPI (1980-1994 1 linear foot), subseries contains information regarding the TIMED Doppler Interferometer (TIDI), Total Ozone Mapping (TOMS), Balloon Rotator, Antarctic Magnetometer, and the Multiplex Fabry-Perot Interferometer (MFPI). The MFPI is a remote sensing instrument that measures the trace gases in the Earth's atmosphere. Contained in the series are notes and schematics regarding the swinging etalon component. There are also notes, drawings, and tests regarding the balloon rotator and the Antarctic magnetometer. The bulk of the series covers the design and testing of the TIDI and TOMS projects. Both projects contributed to the study of the Earth's atmosphere. Contained within the series are meeting notes, designs, schematics, and viewgraphs of the two projects.
    - 1987-1995, 22 folders (Box 7)
    - 1982-1996, 2 folders (Box 7)